A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests, Series N FA323
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Missionary and Church Groups
  - Missionary and Church Groups - World University Service, 1953-1960 (Box 50, Folder 399)
    Gifts by John D. Rockefeller 3rd and Martha B. Rockefeller for student aid. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Martha B. Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel.
  - Missionary and Church Groups - World Student Service Fund - Fridjof Nansen House, 1949-1960 (Box 50, Folder 400)
    Financial data. House in Goettingen, Germany, anonymous donation to needs of House. Correspondents include W. J. Kitchen, Dana S. Creel, Olar Brennhovd, David Rockefeller.
  - Missionary and Church Groups - Rural Church Institute, 1948-1955 (Box 50, Folder 401)
    Financial needs of Institute, John D. Rockefeller 3rd's contributions, printed materials. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    4.25
  - Missionary and Church Groups - New England Town and Country Church Commission, 1930-1947 (Box 51, Folder 402)
    Conference with Mrs. Hilda Ives and Dr. Kenneth C. MacArthur on "Larger Parishes;" reports, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s interest, contributions list, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge to annual budgets, additional pledges. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., T. Arnett, Kenneth MacArthur, Willard S. Richardson, Hilda Ives, Arthur W. Packard, E. Stanley, A. E. Jones, H. F. Kazmier, John A. Tuckerman.
    4.41
- Protestant Council of the City of New York
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - New York Federation of Churches, 1897-1913 (Box 51, Folder 403)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions to general work and Vacation Bible Schools. Publication of Dr. George J. Fisher's pamphlet on sex education of adolescent boys, payment of pledges on behalf of Federation and Billy Sunday Association work; plans for headquarters building, memorial to William Henry Hall; renewal of annual contributions; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge through Federation to Bethel African Methodist Episcopal Church. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Thomas B. Appleget, Willard S. Richardson.
    132
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - New York Federation of Churches, 1914-1927 (Box 51, Folder 404)
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - New York Federation of Churches, 1928-1945 (Box 51, Folder 405)
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York, 1943-1951 (Box 51, Folder 406)
    Organization of the Council, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge, activities of the Council, election of David Rockefeller as member of Council, David Rockefeller's address February 4, 1952, appeals. Correspondents include E. C. Carder, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., E. B. Young, H. Fish, David Rockefeller, Cleveland Dodge, Dana S. Creel.
    132.1
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York, 1947-1950 (Box 51, Folder 406A)
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York, 1952-1961 (Box 52, Folder 407)
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York, 1952-1961 (Box 52, Folder 407A)
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - Division of Christian Education, 1944-1947 (Box 52, Folder 408)
    David Rockefeller's contribution to Committee for Religious Education on Released Time and Division of Christian Education. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, David Rockefeller.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - A. M. Witwer, Jr., 1945-1946 (Box 52, Folder 409)
    Chaplain Witwer's praise of John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s address at Protestant Council, views of Christian unity, employment by Protestant Council, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s payment of his salary. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - Contributions, 1943-1953 (Box 52, Folder 410)
    Contributions by family to budget, renewal of contributions. Rockefeller Brothers Fund giving. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, E. C. Carder, C. Dodge.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - Contributions, 1954-1961 (Box 52, Folder 411)
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - Contributions, 1954 (Box 52, Folder 411A)
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address, 1944-1954 (Box 52, Folder 412)
    Opening dinner of Protestant Council campaign, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s acceptance of invitation to be speaker, program, letters of congratulations, gratitude at letters requesting copies of speech. Correspondents include C. Dodge, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., E. C. Carder, Nelson A. Rockefeller, C. W. Petitt.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address - Bishop DeWolfe Criticism, 1945 (Box 52, Folder 413)
    Criticism by Episcopal bishop of Long Island on John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s January 31, 1945 speech, rebuke of bishop by seventeen Episcopal clergymen. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., E. C. Carder.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address - Copies, 1945 (Box 52, Folder 414)
    Typescript and printed copy of address.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address - Printing of Speech - Pamphlet Form, 1945 (Box 52, Folder 415)
    Plans for publication, circularization, testimonials received. Correspondents include Burnham Carter, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., E. C. Carder, S. M. Cavert.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address - Publication in Reader's Digest, 1945 (Box 52, Folder 416)
    Publication plans, permission granted for reprint rights. Correspondents include B. Carter, Corinne Johnson.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address - Publicity and Clippings, 1945-1949 (Box 52, Folder 417)
    Newspaper clippings, publication of address in books, booklets, pamphlets.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address - Letters, January-March 1945 (Box 53, Folder 418)
    Letters commenting upon John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s address, letters acknowledging receipt of each. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address - Letters, April 1945-1958 (Box 53, Folder 419)
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address - Letters, 1946 (Box 53, Folder 419A)
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address - Letters - Anonymous, 1945 (Box 53, Folder 420)
    Praise of Address, unsigned letters from religious lunatics.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address - Religious Tracts (Box 53, Folder 421)
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - Billy Graham Crusade - New York, 1956-1960 (Box 53, Folder 422)
    Family contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Dana S. Creel.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - Billy Graham Crusade - New York, 1956-1958 (Box 53, Folder 422A)
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - Protestant Chapel at International Airport, 1958-1961 (Box 53, Folder 423)
    At International Airport. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel.
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - Protestant Chapel at International Airport, 1959-1960 (Box 53, Folder 423A)
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York - Protestant Fund of Greater New York, 1946-1948 (Box 54, Folder 424)
    Organization chart, budgets, clippings, reports on dinner, status of campaign, liquidation of fund. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s February 1947 pledge. Correspondents include C. E. Dodge, Arthur W. Packard, J. G. Blaine.
    132.2
- Religious Education
  - Religious Education - Religious Education Association, 1906-1960 (Box 54, Folder 425)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions, work of the Association, budgets. Correspondents include W. H. Faunce, Frederick T. Gates, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    57
  - Religious Education - Religious Education Association, 1952-1960 (Box 54, Folder 425A)
  - Religious Education - Religious Education Association - Pledges, 1902-1934 (Box 54, Folder 426)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge to Convention for Religious Education work of the various Commissions of Association, conditions of pledge. Pledges, February 1930, March 2, 1931, May 29, 1930. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Religious Education - Schools of Religious Instruction, 1929-1958 (Box 54, Folder 427)
    Invitation to participate in National Council on Higher Education, needs of Pacific School of Religion, denials of appeals for funds. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, A. C. McGiffert.
    57.1
  - Religious Education - Printed Material, 1940-1941 (Box 54, Folder 428)
    57.2
  - Religious Education - Interdenominational Committee on Released Time, 1941 (Box 54, Folder 429)
  - Religious Education - Interdenominational Committee on Released Time, 1942-1944 (Box 54, Folder 430)
  - Religious Education - Interdenominational Committee on Released Time - Appeal Letters and Payments, 1942-1944 (Box 54, Folder 431)
    David Rockefeller's pledge to Protestant Committee for Week-day Religious Education, payment of Miss Claribel Goodwin's salary, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge to budget of Interdenominational Committee for Religious Education on Released Time, contributions by other members of Rockefeller family. Correspondents include C. E. Dodge, W. R. Howlett, David Rockefeller.
    57.2C
  - Religious Education - Interdenominational Committee on Released Time - Appeal Letters and Payments, 1941-1943 (Box 54, Folder 431A)
  - Religious Education - National Council on Religion in Higher Education, 1921-1960 (Box 55, Folder 432)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge to Councils of School of Religion, work of Council, appointment of Fellows. Pledges, November 6, 1929, September 15, 1932. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, C. E. Dodge, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Chas. F. Kent, H. Fosdick, Arthur W. Packard, R. H. Edwards.
    57.3
  - Religious Education - American Association on Religion, 1926-1929 (Box 55, Folder 433)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution to budget, reports. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, C. E. Dodge, W. H. P. Faunce, Chas. H. Brent, O. D. Foster.
    57.4
  - Religious Education - Tarrytown Weekday Church School of Religion, 1941-1944 (Box 55, Folder 434)
    Plans for conducting school, financial needs, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution. Correspondents include Horace H. Hunt, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Religious Education - North American Board for Study of Religion in Higher Education, 1932-1940 (Box 55, Folder 435)
    Plans for conference, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge to Board. Correspondents include O. D. Foster, Arthur W. Packard, Francis C. Kelley.
    57.5
  - Religious Education - Greater New York Coordinating Committee on Released Time of Jews, Protestants, etc., 1945-1959 (Box 55, Folder 436)
    List of members, financial statement, minutes, denials of appeals. Correspondents include Chas. H. Tuttle, W. R. Howlett, David Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel.
    57.21
  - Religious Education - Greater New York Coordinating Committee on Released Time of Jews, Protestants, etc., 1945-1959 (Box 55, Folder 436A)
- Religious Organizations
  - Religious Organizations - New York City Sunday School Association, 1916-1923 (Box 55, Folder 437)
    Plans for Parlor Conference at Mr. Rockefeller's home on topic "The Boy, The War and the Church." John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions to Laymen's Committee for the conduct of the Greater New York Home Visitation, comp equipment. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, A. F. Schauffler, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., George A. Goodridge.
    141.1&2
  - Religious Organizations - Metropolitan Federation - Daily Vacation Bible Schools, 1927-1944 (Box 55, Folder 438)
    Secretary's report, financial statement, work of Federation. Contributions. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Hugh W. Magill, W. R. Howlett.
    141
  - Religious Organizations - Miscellaneous Sunday School Associations, 1918-1952 (Box 55, Folder 439)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s article on Bible Class Study, publication of pamphlet, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s statement on Sunday Schools to the International Convention, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller's contribution to World Association of Daily Vacation Bible Schools. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., W. C. Pearce.
    141.4
  - Religious Organizations - Miscellaneous Sunday School Associations - Ocean County Council of Religious Education, 1924-1929 (Box 55, Folder 440)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, N. W. Davis.
  - Religious Organizations - Westchester County Sunday School Association, 1917-1943 (Box 56, Folder 441)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution to Westchester and Putnam Counties Young Women's Christian Association. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, W. H. Baxley.
    141.5
  - Religious Organizations - Committee on Religious Life in the Nation's Capital, 1942 (Box 56, Folder 442)
    Work of Committee, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution, inability of Committee to prosecute plan, cancellation of pledge. Correspondents include Owen J. Roberts, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    141.6
  - Religious Organizations - International Council of Religious Education, 1923-1932 (Box 56, Folder 443)
    Plans for Crusade for Christian Education, annual reports, contributions. Correspondents include Paul D. Eddy, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur w. Packard, Roy G. Ross.
    141.7
  - Religious Organizations - International Council of Religious Education, 1933-1952 (Box 56, Folder 444)
  - Religious Organizations - International Council of Religious Education - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Address, September 1942 (Box 56, Folder 445)
    Address in behalf of International Council of Religious Education, plans for international broadcast, comments about address. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John B. Ketcham.
  - Religious Organizations - Religious Matters (Miscellaneous) and Councils of Religious Education
    Appeals denied for contributions to various Councils of Religious Education and movements. Some small gifts for special purposes. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, Samuel L. Hamilton, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Laurance S. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller.
    141.8
    - Religious Organizations - Religious Matters (Miscellaneous) and Councils of Religious Education, 1926-1953 (Box 56, Folder 446)
    - Religious Organizations - Religious Matters (Miscellaneous) and Councils of Religious Education, 1954-1957 (Box 56, Folder 447)
    - Religious Organizations - Religious Matters (Miscellaneous) and Councils of Religious Education, 1954-1957 (Box 56, Folder 447A)
    - Religious Organizations - Religious Matters (Miscellaneous) and Councils of Religious Education, 1958-1961 (Box 57, Folder 448)
  - Religious Organizations - Association for a United Church of America, 1944-1958 (Box 57, Folder 449)
    Plans for the Association, printed materials, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s anonymous contribution. Correspondents include E. Stanley Jones, Hilda Ives, John H. Ryder, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    141.9
  - Religious Organizations - Academy of Religion and Mental Health, 1954-1961 (Box 57, Folder 450)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller and Rockefeller Brothers Fund contributions and interest in work of academy. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel, H. C. Merserve.
    141.10
    Open per KWR, December 2004
  - Religious Organizations - The Christophers, 1948-1961 (Box 57, Folder 451)
    Printed materials, clippings, publicity. Correspondents include Y. Allen, Dana S. Creel, Arthur W. Packard.
    141.11
  - Religious Organizations - Laymen's National Committee, 1940-1961 (Box 57, Folder 452)
    Work of organization, printed appeals for funds. Correspondents include Thomas M. Debevoise, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Frank Kingdon.
    141.12
  - Religious Organizations - Laymen's National Committee, 1957-1961 (Box 57, Folder 452A)
  - Religious Organizations - United Stewardship Council, 1949-1950 (Box 57, Folder 453)
    Work of the Council, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution, reports. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Harry S. Myers.
    141.13
  - Religious Organizations - Church Unity, 1947-1957 (Box 57, Folder 454)
    Letters from clergymen presenting idea of one church. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
    141.14
  - Religious Organizations - New York City Mission Society, 1927-1961 (Box 58, Folder 455)
    Activities of the Society, plans for interdenominational church project near Navy Yard and Good Neighbor Community House. Request participation. Printed material. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, C. H. Sears, David W. Barry, Y. Allen, David R. Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel.
    141.15
  - Religious Organizations - New York City Mission Society - Contributions, 1950-1961 (Box 58, Folder 456)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions to Society. Also, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Mary French Rockefeller, Rodman Rockefeller. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel, Kenneth D. Miller.
  - Religious Organizations - New York City Mission Society - Printed Material (Box 58, Folder 457)
  - Religious Organizations - World Welfare, 1952-1953 (Box 58, Folder 458)
    Appeals for funds, work of World Welfare and Peace, Inc., Armenian, Greek and Syrian relief activities. Correspondents include Arthur Jones, Charles V. Vickrey.
    141.16
  - Religious Organizations - World Education, Inc., 1958-1960 (Box 58, Folder 459)
    Clippings, appeals, no aid.
    141.17
  - Religious Organizations - World Literacy, 1951-1957 (Box 58, Folder 460)
    Frank Laubach and his World Literacy organization. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Frank Laubach.
  - Religious Organizations - Laubach Literacy and Mission Fund, 1957-1960 (Box 58, Folder 461)
    Sends new book. Request for aid, declined. Correspondents include F. C. Laubach.
    141.171
  - Religious Organizations - Congregational and Christian Churches, USA, 1938-1961 (Box 58, Folder 462)
    Activities. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    141.18
  - Religious Organizations - Christ the King Foundation
    Episcopal center for higher education. Nelson A. Rockefeller's son-in-law a participant. Appeals. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Robert Pierson.
    141.19
    - Religious Organizations - Christ the King Foundation, 1957-1958 (Box 58, Folder 463)
    - Religious Organizations - Christ the King Foundation, 1959-1961 (Box 59, Folder 464)
  - Religious Organizations - World Council of Christian Education, 1928-1958 (Box 59, Folder 465)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s declination of appeals for contributions to World's Sunday School Association, change of name to World Council of Christian Education, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution anonymous to visual aids program and for expenses of delegates to convention at Toronto. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Raymond B. Fosdick, Eddie Rickenbacker, G. Bromley, Oxnam, J. Arthur Rank, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    141.41
  - Religious Organizations - Foundation for Religious Action in the Social and Civil Order, 1953-1959 (Box 59, Folder 466)
    Appeals for aid to interfaith group fighting communism. Appeals declined. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, C. W. Lowry.
    141.20
  - Religious Organizations - American Unitarian Association, 1955-1959 (Box 59, Folder 467)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller made contribution to 1958 Chicago meeting of religious thinkers from all over the world. Unitarian Universalist union. Correspondents include Harry C. Merserve, Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    141.21
  - Religious Organizations - National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America (NCCC)
    Minutes of meeting of Planning Committee, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge, budget, work of the Council, report of Buck Hill Falls Conference, Rockefeller Brothers Fund contributions, printed materials, studies and pronouncements of the National Council, desire of Council to purchase site for office building. Communist infiltration accusation. Correspondents include E. F. Adams, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel, S. M. Cavert, Henry Knox Sherrill, Phillip Keebler, Roy G. Ross, Eugene C. Blake.
    141.82
    - Religious Organizations - NCCC, 1952 (Box 59, Folder 468)
    - Religious Organizations - NCCC, 1952 (Box 59, Folder 469)
    - Religious Organizations - NCCC, 1951 (Box 60, Folder 470)
    - Religious Organizations - NCCC, 1951-1952 (Box 60, Folder 471)
  - Religious Organizations - National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America (NCCC) - Contributions
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution to Planning committee of National Council, to Department of International Justice and Goodwill, David Rockefeller's contribution to Union Church of Monterrey, annual contributions by other members of family. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John F. Dulles, S. M. Cavert, David Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Henry K. Sherrill, Roy Ross.
    - Religious Organizations - NCCC - Contributions, 1957-1961 (Box 60, Folder 472)
    - Religious Organizations - NCCC - Contributions, 1953-1957 (Box 60, Folder 473)
    - Religious Organizations - NCCC - Contributions, 1957 (Box 60, Folder 473A)
    - Religious Organizations - NCCC - Contributions, 1951-1956 (Box 60, Folder 473B)
    - Religious Organizations - NCCC - Contributions, 1949-1953 (Box 60, Folder 474)
  - Religious Organizations - National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America (NCCC) - "Frontiers of Faith" Program, 1951-1956 (Box 60, Folder 475)
  - Religious Organizations - National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America (NCCC) - Contributions, 1948-1951 (Box 60, Folder 476)
  - Religious Organizations - National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America (NCCC) - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Contribution, 1957 (Box 61, Folder 477)
    $50,000 pledge. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel.
  - Religious Organizations - National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America (NCCC) - Christian Ministry in National Parks, 1953-1959 (Box 61, Folder 478)
    Reports on activities, through National Churches of Christ. Correspondents include Y. Allen, Rev. Warren W. Ost.
  - Religious Organizations - National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America (NCCC) - Christian Ministry in National Parks, 1960 (Box 61, Folder 479)
  - Religious Organizations - National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America (NCCC) - Contributions, 1953 (Box 61, Folder 480)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution to Planning Committee of National Council, to Department of International Justice and Goodwill, David Rockefeller's contribution to Union Church of Monterrey, annual contributions by other members of family. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John F. Dulles, S. M. Cavert, David Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Henry K. Sherrill, Roy Ross.